Hello, I'm William
Zeloga, and this is a
presentation of
Pathology of Pulmonary
Vascular Diseases. My
contact information is
on that slide. Feel
free to contact me.
Here's the objectives, and
we're going to start with
pulmonary embolism, hemorrhages,
and infarcts. Okay, so
this is going to be different
categories of disorders
that can occur within the
lungs, and then we're going
to end with pulmonary
hypertension there's going to be
a little bit more involved
and a couple of specific
types of syndromes good pasture
syndrome and granulomatosis
with polyangiitis formerly
known as Wegener's
granulomatosis but people don't
use it anymore well you might
read it somewhere okay but
you want to know how this
differs from similar diseases
one of those would be
good pasture syndrome so I'll
be discussing both of them
here's a review the pulmonary
arteries shown here in
purple on the right image
are from the right ventricle
and they perfuse the alveoli
okay and they're shown
here on the image on the left
then on the left diagram.
And they carry
deoxygenated blood to
the alveoli, which
then oxygenates them.
And there's another set
of arteries known as
the bronchial arteries.
The bronchi are supplied
by these bronchial
arteries, and those are
going to be from the
left ventricle supply,
such as the aorta,
intercostal arteries, and
they're going to perfuse
the conduction airways.
Here in the lung, there's
anastomosis, there's
a bronchial pulmonary
anastomosis that occurs.
Some of the bronchial
blood goes down the
azagosed venous system,
and a little bit is added
to the oxygenated blood
from the pulmonary artery,
and that goes out into
the pulmonary vein.
Okay, so the first
entity we're going
to discuss, really
important, see this
quite a bit, is
pulmonary embolism.
It's the third most
common condition
worldwide, acute
cardiovascular I should say,
worldwide.
Rare in kids, common
after your age is 75.
People at risk are
going to include your
inpatients more
than the population.
Most clots are going to be
including large arteries
and they're going to, and
these clots are going to
be embolic. They're usually
going to be from deep
leg vein thrombi, so the
thrombi will, 95%, the thrombi
will grow and develop
and a portion of it might
break off and then travel
through the circulation
and then lodge at the smallest
vessel that it can get
to and possibly cause a
thromboembolic infarction.
So deep vein,
late vein thrombi,
usually the femoral vein.
Rarely you can have other
types like a septic art
infarct that's from
infected embolus material,
fat embolus, air amniotic
fluid. You can have neoplastic
cells that will form an
embolus as well. Here's
an example of a phantom
bliss. So a lot of the bone
marrow is fat. So a small
bone marrow embly can be
seen after vigorous
chest compressions during
resuscitation and obviously
often in those people who die.
Usually in patients with
predisposing conditions
this will this occurs
and those people
will have an increased
risk of thrombosis.
So for example,
hypercoagulable states
and I list a few here.
Mutations in their genes
or antiphospholipid
syndrome. Secondary types
will be hypercoagulable
states not of the coagulation
system itself as the
primary one but due to
other diseases which affect
the coagulation system
like heart disease cancer
pregnancy contraceptives
or being post-operative
both a lot of those people
are immobilized in bed
for a few days maybe they
want to get them up as
soon as they can but and
include people with hip
fractures those are people
are particularly high risk
catheter catheters that
are indwelling and lines
I mean, central venous
lines that are indwelling.
Okay,
to make yourself aware of
this, that there could be
a possibility of
thromboembolism, Birchow came up
with a triad of general
factors that contributed to
thrombosis. Those are going
to be hemodynamic changes,
endothelial injury, and
hypercoagulability. So
if your patient has those
kind of features, and they
are demonstrating possibly
a pulmonary embolism,
then it's probably a
pulmonary embolism, okay?
So the pathophysiology,
there's two main
consequences.
Respiratory compromise,
and that's due to a
non-perfused segment.
Although you get air there,
there's no blood going past.
Or hemodynamic compromise, and
that's caused by obstruction.
So you can get sudden death,
depending on where the
obstruction or obstructions
are. You can have core
pulmonal develop if this is
something that is widespread
throughout the lungs and
cause right-sided heart
failure or core pulmonal, or
if it's small and dispersed,
it can be developed into
pulmonary hypertension.
This is the nature stained
slide of a lung biopsy,
which shows a large
pulmonary, I guess, arteriole
here, and what you see
in here is not a lumen,
but some material which
should not be there.
This is bone.
You can see some of
the osteocytes here.
And this is the bone marrow. So
the marrow has a
lot of fat in it.
And then you see the
erythropoietic tissues that are
there too. So this is a
fragment that came from
bone marrow that embolized
into the lung circulation.
now we're switching to
hemorrhage and infarction
okay large embyli well
we're not switching to
we're going to be discussing
it or we'll be talking
other entities that will
relate to hemorrhage
and infarction a little
bit later large emboli
can large in the main
pulmonary trunk that is
known as a saddle embolus
And if you go back here,
the saddle embolus will
occur right here, okay?
They'll come through
the pulmonary trunk
and dislodge right here,
cutting off the left
and right pulmonary
artery circulations.
And this is an
example of one. This
is one of the
pulmonary arteries.
But here, no, it's not.
It's from the pulmonary,
well, they say from
the left femoral vein.
But this is, I think it's
showing part of, yeah,
this is the conduction, I
mean the pulmonary arterial
system. This is a large
vessel that shows a blood
clot in it, and there's
an immediate danger of
hemodynamic collapse, which
is cardiovascular failure.
Smaller emboli may
travel out to the
smaller peripheral
vessels, and that
can cause hemorrhages
or infarctions.
With your compromised
cardiovascular function,
infarctions may be more likely.
Infarctions are going to
be classically hemorrhagic.
This is a photograph of
a classic hemorrhagic
infarction of the lungs
and that's due to the dual
circulation. I'll explain
a little bit more. You
remember the pulmonary and
the bronchial arteries.
So histologically the
area will show hemorrhagic
areas as is shown
here. So this is dark,
I guess purple, black
area compared to
the normal, you know,
tan peak, spongy
area shown here of
the normal lung.
So this is involving a lobe,
well not a lobe, a segment
of the lung. And if you
do an H&E stain section,
you can see ischemic necrosis
of various structures.
And if an embolism
leads to infarction, and
what I was just
describing, ischemic
necrosis is infarction
of some of the tissue,
then this is what you'll
see within the clot
itself. And that will tell
you the reason that this
is being described, this
is what's known as lines
of zon is because at
autopsy you'll see blood
clots but you need to
understand if those blood
clots were formed before
they were dying before they
died and blood was
flowing or after they died
and blood was not flowing
if it was flowing you'll
see laminated pattern
of light and dark areas.
The dark areas are going
to be red blood cells
and that will be dark
red grossly and will
resemble jelly or what's
known as currant jelly.
And the lighter areas
are going to be
platelets.
Okay.
So the lighter areas
are platelet and
fibrin that's occurring
in flowing blood,
so lighter bands.
And these darker
areas, forget the
current jelly, that's
not current jelly,
but that's going
to be layers of
erythrocytes that are
traveling through the
circulation as this
clot is forming.
Okay.
If there's blood circulation,
then that means you'll
see lines of Zon, and
then it was anti-mortem.
So, to distinguish
that from a post
-mortem clot, the post
-mortem clots will
have the red cells
and solid components
that will be sedimented out
according to gravity into
one layer, and that one
layer of red cells and other
components will look like a
dark red currant jelly. The
other part with serum and
proteins and things like
that will solidify into a
yellow area which will look
like chicken fat and that's
how you tell the two apart.
Red cells will Lysed in
this clot in about 48
hours. The infarctions
that I showed you before
will become paler then
it'll become more red-brown
and that's because the
red cells are broken
down and the hemocytorin
is formed from the iron.
Eventually, you get
a tan-contracted
scar that forms with healing.
Clinical findings.
Many PEs are clinically silent.
They could be small
or really small
and dispersed
throughout the lungs.
So maybe a little short
of breath with exertion or
something like that. But
sometimes silent completely.
So the small ones can be silent
or transient chest
pain or cough.
5% can cause acute
corporal mal, that's
right, sighted heart
failure, shock or death.
And that's typically that large
saddle embolus I described.
If a person is undergoing CPR,
you frequently will
see electromechanical
dissociation on the EKG.
So you have a pulse,
no pulse will be palpated
because no blood is entering,
but you'll still see
that rhythm on the EKG.
If a patient survives,
it can clinically mimic
a myocardial infarction
because you'll have
pain as shown up here,
trouble breathing,
possibly shock.
And those are all
characteristics of MI2.
In the remaining patients
who don't have a silent MI,
you can get
symptoms that occur.
Some of the symptoms may be
what's called a ventilation
perfusion mismatch or VQ
mismatch. Q is perfusion.
And that's when the air
flow and the blood flow in
the lungs is imbalanced.
or an infarction and that
then you'll get in particular
dyspnea and a pleuritic
kind of chest pain that
means with each breath and
you most commonly find that
pleuritic pain friction
rub which is due to
overlying fibrinous pleuritis
a a cough, fever, coughing
up blood, haemophysis,
and that's because emboli
are producing infarction.
You can have calf and
thigh swelling or pain.
I put an asterisk there
because that's referring
to what's known as Homan's
sign. I mean, there
can be pain, but when
you dorsiflex the foot,
you'll have increased
pain, and that can
occur just because you
maybe walked up a lot
of stairs or something
like that, but it
can be present if you
also have a PE, too.
So it's really not
specific or sensitive,
but it can be present
if you have a PE.
If you have recurrent
small embly,
that can cause
pulmonary hypertension
as they occlude vessels
within the lungs,
okay, and the vessels
will become more,
the walls will become
thicker and more,
with less of a lumen.
So,
laboratories that
can help you diagnose
this are, for a
useful screening test,
D-dimer. A normal level
excludes pulmonary embolism,
and that's going to be
in hemodynamically stable
patients. That means they're
at low pretest probability.
They probably didn't
have it. And if it's
negative, D-dimer is
negative, meaning you
suspect that you need
to get it anyway, then
it's probably not a
PE if it's negative.
Definitive diagnosis
is done today with a CT
pulmonary angiogram, or
magnetic resonance type,
and that identifies the
obstructed arteries.
Sometimes, other diagnostics
like a VQ scan may be
required. I put an image
of that. This is a normal
perfusion of the lungs,
and this is after someone
inhales radioactive gas.
that's ventilation, or injected
a radioactive tracer, and
that's the perfusion, Q.
And this is normal
perfusion of the lungs,
and this is abnormal
perfusion. You can
see several areas
which are not perfused.
And that's detected by a
gamma radiation detector,
a scintillation camera.
For deep vein thrombosis,
if you're looking for
a source, and you suspect,
then you can quickly
use a Doppler ultrasound
and diagnose an
obstruction within one
of the veins of the legs.
A chest x-ray isn't sensitive
or specific for PE but
it may disclose a pulmonary
infarction or be normal.
It's a little degradation
product and it's a
product of thrombolysis
okay and that's the medical
treatment thrombolysis
the biological process is
fibrinolysis that's
occurring and that helps
diagnose thrombosis but
that thrombosis could be
anywhere but if you have
signs of PE then the
thrombosis could be a
thromboembolism to the lungs.
Or it could be other
conditions. I list other
conditions down here at the
bottom and so this D-dimer
is not specific because
also well you have DBTs
but malignancy, sepsis,
coronary artery syndrome,
trauma, surgery,
pregnancy may all raise
your D-dimer because
thrombosis is occurring.
So because it
indicates the presence
but does not specify
location or type.
So, a negative D-dimer
does not really change
the probability if someone
has a pulmonary embolism
if people are at high
risk for thrombosis,
okay, with the risk factors
that I've already mentioned.
So, okay, so how could this
be prevented or treated?
So, after a person
has a PE, just after,
it resolves, usually
in young people,
and that's through
fibrinolysis, okay?
If it's unresolved or
multiple small emboli,
that can lead to
pulmonary hypertension and
possibly chronic corpulmonale.
If a person is at high risk
of recurrence, then that
can lead to recurrent
emboli and the same thing.
It's important to note
that that is that if you
have a small PE, that may
predict the larger one.
Okay, so you should be
looking for sources of
why someone could be
producing pulmonary emboli.
Prophylactic therapy
include early ambulation
from those who have
been immobile for
extended periods. There
are compression stockings
and hose that people
can use that will help
with their circulation
of the extremities.
And anticoagulation for those
who are at
particular high risk.
Another treatment which
includes anticoagulation
supportive if they're
at risk for recurrence
and anticoagulation can't
be used is possibly an
inferior vena cava filter
inserted surgically.
The definition of
pulmonary hypertension is
a mean pulmonary artery
pressure greater than
25 millimeters of
mercury that's at rest.
Pulmonary hypertension is
a direct disease of the
arteries and this is a
direct disease but it
has groups that are
categorized based on the
underlying mechanism and
the WHO classified at World
Health Organization and
there's five groups may
have a lot of different
causes between these
different groups and within
these different groups.
So primary pulmonary
hypertension is also
known as PAH, pulmonary
arterial hypertension,
also known as idiopathic. So
the cause isn't exactly known.
And that could be a
diverse collection of
diseases on almost
all will be affecting
the small pulmonary
arteries or arterioles.
And then there's pulmonary
hypertension due to left
heart failure. That's the
most frequent cause overall.
And that's due to lung
disease or hypoxia,
chronic thromboembolic or other
obstructions that can occur.
and the unclear and
multifactorial mechanisms.
So the common causes
are secondary causes.
I list some of them here.
For example, obstructive
sleep apnea, and that
is common with obesity
and can cause hypoxemia,
which is one of the causes that
can produce pulmonary
hypertension,
congenital or required
heart disease,
chronic obstruction or
interstitial lung disease.
That increases
pulmonary resistance.
And that can be produced
by recurrent thromboemboli.
Autoimmune diseases can
produce interstitial
disease. Notably,
systemic sclerosis
can involve the
pulmonary vessels.
Okay.
Most cases are going
to be structural.
and those are going to
be caused by conditions
that can increase pulmonary
blood flow, in which case
the pulmonary arteries
will react and become
more muscular and the
lumens will become smaller,
or increase pulmonary
vascular resistance if they're
constricted and they'll
become more muscular,
or if there's outflow or
flow from the lungs into
the heart that's providing
resistance. So there's
more resistance flow from
the lung to the heart,
left heart, that can produce
pulmonary hypertension,
so secondary causes.
And here's an example of
another thromboembolus
that's within the lungs.
And what you see here
is fibrous bands forming
while healing is
occurring. Because as the
blood, as the healing
occurs, lumens start to
develop within this
thromus to allow blood flow
to go through. So small
capillaries will develop,
and then you'll have
blood flow occurring.
So primary pulmonary
hypergensin pathogenesis,
that's also the PAH
form, is learned
from uncommon familial
forms. So something was
learned because from
when they noticed that
it was being inherited
from family members.
The first mutation that
was discovered was a
germline mutation in the
BMPR2 receptor. Okay.
And this is an inactivating
gene mutation that
leads to insufficiency
of the receptor. And
then there's dysfunction
and proliferation of
endothelial and vascular
smooth muscle cells.
Other mutations
occur, but it was
discovered that the
ones they discovered
also converge on
this BMPR2 pathway.
Here's an H&E stained
tissue section of the lung
showing an arterial, a
thickened arterial. which
is healing, so it's
forming these small
cavities. You can see a
little bit of blood within
this one. So this is forming
when the thromboembolism
starts to contract
and fibrinolysis is
occurring. So you get some
small arteries forming,
and this is still fibrotic
tissue involved in the
healing process, and these
are inflammatory cells
that are trying to assist
the healing process.
And this is known as
a plexiform lesion.
And plexiform means web-like.
And that's the
characteristics of advanced
pulmonary hypertension,
these plexiform lesions.
All forms are going to be
associated with the medial
hypertrophy. That's going
to mean the tunica media
versus the tunica externa
or the tunica intima.
so that's where the of the
muscular portion of the
muscular arteries are and
the elastic is as well
so there's grades for the
changes that you see in
the arteries okay so grades
4 through 6 that's when
you get to into the
irreversible type of conditions
if you get a biopsy grade
3 your borderline so
you want to keep them
below 3, at 3 or below,
because then 1 or 2 might
be potentially reversible.
So if you get a biopsy and
you see medial hypertrophy,
nothing else, then that's
potentially reversible.
If you see medial hypertrophy
with some intimal cell
proliferation within the
vessel, that could also be
reversible. But if you get
medial hypertrophy, intimal
proliferation, and fibrosis,
and that's borderline,
your risk of reversibility
goes way down.
But if you start getting
plexiform lesions, then you
get into the inversible,
irreversible categories,
and if you get vein-like
muscular arteries, hypertrophy
muscular arteries, and
angiomatoid, that means
arterial artery-like, and
necrotizing arteritis, that'll
be irreversible form of
pulmonary hypertension.
So here's some of the
grades. Here's grade one.
Okay, so you'll see
that medial hypertrophy.
You don't see a lot of
other things. Okay, here's
the tunica entoma, tunica
externa, but there's
a lot of extra smooth
muscle and fibroblasts.
Okay,
but no fibrosis.
No intimal proliferation.
Here, you do see
a lot of collagen
being deposited. That's this
highline pink material
that's associated
with the spindle-like
nuclei. Those are
fibroblasts and they're
producing a lot of
collagen. So you get
entomal fibrosis here,
you know, close to the lumen.
This one is still open,
but this one is very much
constricted. So you get
narrow vessel lumens and
blood can't flow through
that effectively results
in pulmonary hypertension
the diagnosis if you do
an EKG you can see right
axis deviation due to
hypertrophy on a chest x-ray
you can see pulmonary artery
enlargement and tapering
of distal vessels with
echo so on imaging you can
see dilation of the
pulmonary artery the atria
hypertrophy and dilation.
If you do catheterization of
the right atria, this is
the gold standard and that
directly measures the
pressure in the lung arteries
and it shows increased
pulmonary artery pressure.
Pulmonary hypertension,
these are clinical
findings and treatments.
Typically you only see an
advanced disease. Early
signs are subtle, maybe
a little shorter breath
with exercise, maybe
more tired than usual.
In idiopathic disease,
that usually presents with
dyspnea and fatigue,
sometimes anginal chest pain.
That progresses to severe
respiratory distress, cyanosis,
so you're progressing
towards the core pulmonale
that will occur later if
you don't do something.
You can get peripheral edema
because it's the right heart,
JVD, parasternal lift,
do the hypertrophy,
and then as it
progresses more, you can
have death from
decompensated corpulmonal.
You also will see
thrombomobly and pneumonia,
and that can occur in
80% of patients within 2
to 5 years if nothing is
done as it progresses.
So most of the patients
are going to be older,
often greater than 65,
and as age goes up, And
that's when you get the
underlying heart and lung
diseases that are going
to contribute to this.
Women have a slightly common
more incidence than men.
Subtypes, like the
number one category, PAH,
frequently involve
younger folks,
30s to 60s, and
middle-aged women.
Rarely is this seen in kids.
Treatment involves treating
an underlying cause.
For PAH, vasovilators.
For secondary disease,
something that directly
affects the trigger,
like the thromboembolism
or hypoxemia.
Lung transplantation may
be the only definitive
treatment, but that's
in selected patients.
Here's pulmonary hemorrhage
syndrome, and this is
just a generic slide of
what hemorrhage within
the pulmonary hemorrhage
syndrome would look like.
There's a couple of
examples of what may cause
that. There are many
others. For example, CHF may
cause this, but there's
good pasture syndrome,
and polyangiitis with
granulomatosis we'll go over,
but there's also hypersensitivity
angiitis, and lupus,
idiopathic pulmonary
hemosiderosis will be discussed.
And what you see here
is diffuse hemorrhages
that are within
the alveoli, okay?
So this should be an open
space surrounded by type
1 and 2 pneumocytes, but
instead you see some red
cells which are red here
but also a lot of other
cells which are macrophages
and they're engulfing those
red cells which shouldn't
be there and they're
breaking it down and turning
some of that into some
of the red cells iron into
hemocytorin okay so that's
that's what it looks like
and those are known as
hemocytorin-laden sac
macrophages that consume those
red cells producing a
siderin, or siderophages.
And those siderophages,
if you do a Prussian
Blue stain, to prove
that it's broken down red
blood cells, is a stain
called Prussian Blue that
identifies the iron derived
from the hemoglobin,
and that's going to
be in the macrophages.
Good pressure syndrome
involves the lung and is an
anti-glomerular basement
membrane antibody disease.
And it has pulmonary involvement.
pulmonary involvement
because it's an autoimmune
disease that not only
affects the lung, but also
the kidneys. It affects
basement membranes. And it
affects basement membranes
that have this type of
collagen, collagen 4, but
also the non-collagenous
domain of the alpha 3 chain,
but collagen 4. And it's
a circulating auto-anybody
that's going to affect
the kidney and the lungs.
Most cases are going to
occur in the teens and 20s
with the male predominance,
unlike most autoimmune
diseases which will have
a female predominance
and the majority are going
to be active smokers.
It's also called
antiglomerular basement
membrane disease if you
only have renal disease.
So it's caused by pathogenic
antibodies which cause
inflammatory construction,
destruction of the basement
membranes in the lung,
alveoli, and kidney
glomeruli. Okay, so you
get necrotizing hemorrhagic
interstitial pneumonitis and
lungs and usually rapidly
progressive glomerulone
apritis within the kidneys.
The trigger what causes
all this is not known
but scientists have
discovered something as with
other autoimmune disorders
it's associated with
certain HLA types like
this DRB1, 1501 and 1502.
Clinically, so this
will be an autopsy, you
see heavy lungs, these
are lungs that are
bisected with areas of
red-brown consolidation.
Okay,
that's due to
destruction of those
alveoli and hemorrhages
within the lungs.
Histopathologically,
is shown in this next
slide, this is immunofluorescent
microscopy, So an
antibody has a fluorophore
that reacts with
basement membranes in
this lung tissue section
here. And if you fluoresce
it, you'll see the
basement membrane antibodies
that are attached.
So interalveolar hemorrhages,
hemocytarine macrophages
on histopathology.
Later, fibrous thickening
of the septa and hyperplasia
of the type 2 pneumocytes.
The kidneys will show
the glomerulonephritis,
it'll be what's known as
a, will show proliferative
glomerulositis,
glomerulonephritis, a lot of
extra cells, and crescentic
glomerulonephritis, which
means it'll start to
obstruct Bowman's capsule,
Bowman's space, and then
GFR goes way down because
you can't produce the
tissue scent because of the
abnormality. And this occurs
in a patient with what
is known as rapidly
progressive glomerulonephritis.
So some other findings and
treatments usually begins
with hemoptysis, so blood
notice when you cough.
And testectomy can
show the consolidation
because the blood
is in the alveoli.
Soon after those symptoms,
the kidney will be
affected and can lead and
will lead to rapidly
progressive renal failure.
The most common cause
of death is the renal
disorder and the resulting
iremia that occurs.
Since it's autoimmune,
immune suppressives
are infected like
corticosteroids and
cyclophosphamide.
There is a procedure that
the blood bank performs
known as plasmapheresis,
And that can remove the anti
-basement membrane antibody
from the circulation.
And there's other possible
mediators of immunologic
injury that may be there
that can also be removed. And
then you replace that plasma
with the antibodies and
other stuff with fresh
plasma that doesn't have it.
So that's commonly done
with immunosuppressive
therapy that further inhibits
antibody production. And
that will help the lungs
and the kidneys improve.
So Wegener's
granulomatosis, but we don't
use that anymore, it's
known as granulomatosis
with polyangiitis or
DPA, autoimmune, it
mostly involves the
upper respiratory system.
But it's also going to involve
the lungs, I mean the kidneys.
And it's associated with
anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic
antibody, or C-ANCA in
95% of cases and this
is just another name
for that CINCA PR3 INCA.
Hemophysis as before is
common presenting and it's
usually occurs child of the
middle age about four years
is average age males more
than females if you do a
lung biopsy that's the could
provide tissue that could
give you this diagnosis
but you can also do a renal
biopsy and that can give
your diagnosis too if they
have that affecting if they
have it affecting their
kidneys important features that
you'll see are capillaritis
in the lungs and poorly
formed granulomas and what
does a met necrotizing
fast vasculitis with the
following features okay so this
is an autoimmune vasculitis
that's why it's called
polyangiitis you can see
necrotizing granulomas of
the upper respiratory tract
and lungs or the lungs and
the granulomas are going to
be associated with a
geographic pattern of necrosis.
And this is going to be of
small and medium-sized vessels.
If renal disease is
present, once again,
you can see proliferative or
necrotizing crescentic
glomerulonephritis.
Here is some pathology, and
the lungs will grossly, if
they're bisected like this,
show cavitating lesions
of the necrotic tissue and
injured tissue here that's
undergoing healing but often
will have cavities in it.
Histopathologically,
you'll see irregular-shaped
geographic necrosis.
Let's see, here's the,
what's known as the
geographic necrosis. And this
is a lot of inflammatory
cells within this H&E
stained lung biopsy that
shows an arterial here.
Well,
you can't really tell,
hardly no lumen left.
A lot of inflammatory
cells which are
invading the layers
of this blood vessel.
And with a lot of inflammation
around it. and necrosis.
If you have all
those inflammatory
cells affecting the
blood vessels like
that and you'll
see neutrophils too
when you have the neutrophils
that's a leukocyteoclastic
vasculitis. And you see
this darker area, that's
just debris that was formed
by the tissue destruction
around this vessel and
within the lung branch.
Okay.
Okay. So, pathogenesis
and treatment, it's
usually T cells, T cell
mediated hypersensitivity
to some inhaled microbial
environmental agents,
scientists are still
sorting that through.
But the presence of
granulomas and the dramatic
response to immunosuppressives
shows that it very likely
could be that hypersensitivity.
and it's a necrotizing
medium small vessel
vasculitis of these structures
and treatment is going to
be similar to good pastures
because they're similar
type entities with their
differences that I've noted
in the slides for that
idiopathic pulmonary
hemocenterosis
is a rare disorder with
that occurs intermittently
okay it's diffuse
mostly involved involving
younger children and
that the hemosiderosis
is due to alveolar
hemorrhages okay in males
and females even though it
involves mostly other
children as big incidence
is about 27 years mostly
in young children.
I think I've got
to change this.
But it does occur mostly
in young children. I don't
know why I put the peak
incidence 27 years here.
Scratch that.
So the cause and
pathogenesis are not known.
But it has a
favorable response to
immunosuppression and
these are some of the
suppressants that are commonly
used so an immunologic
mechanism is suspected
to be involved
so you get recurrent
current alveolar bleeding
without an identifiable
cause it usually presents
as insidious cough
hemolysis and anemia and if
you do a test x-ray
you'll see the infiltrates
and but and then
you do the treatment
but this is a
diagnosis of exclusion
you have to rule out all other
causes of pulmonary
hemorrhage first.
Here's some of the
histopathology,
and this is the same
H&E stain slide I showed
you before. You see
macrophages, you see
siderophages in some blood within
the pulmonary alveoli,
and here's a Prussian blue
stain, you know, showing
what we showed you before.
The lungs are increased
in weight because they're,
you know, infiltrated
with blood and they're
going to be consolidated
because the air spaces are
filled with blood. You'll
see sederophages. The
hallmark is going to be
hemorrhage, sederophages,
hemocytorin, and necrosis
of the alveolar walls.
There's no vasculitis,
capillatoritis,
no kind of inflammation.
Here's a summary,
embolism infarct is usually
hemorrhagic of the lungs,
hypertension,
primary idiopathic
disorder associated with
this gene mutation,
and there are other
causes associated with
a few classification.
Good Pasteur Syndrome
involves the lung and
the kidneys, it's
autoimmune, usually male,
autoantibodies to
this type of collagen.
Granulatosis with polyangiitis,
autoimmune, associated
with this antibody.
It's a C-ANCA antibody
known as PR3A.
Necrotizing vasculitis
with that triad, mycrosis,
granulomas, and
vasculitis. And that can be
in the upper respiratory
tract or lungs, involves
small and medium-sized
vessels, and possibly
renal disease, where you
see glomerulonephritis.
Idiopathic pulmonary
hemosiderosis, it's rare.
children, intermittent
response to
immunosuppressants, and
a diagnosis of exclusion.
Thank you, and here is the
link to the feedback form.